这里是伯克村
This is Berk.
绝望谷向北航行十二天
It's 12 days north of Hopeless and a few
到达极寒地以南
degrees south of Freezing to Death.
它就座落在痛苦之经线上
It's located solidly on the Meridian of Misery.
我的村庄  一言以蔽之  坚固
My village. In a word: sturdy.
它有七代人的历史
It's been here for seven generations
但每所建筑仍崭新如初
but every single building is new.
我们打渔  狩猎  享受迷人的日落
We have fishing, hunting, and a charming view of the sunsets.
唯一的麻烦就是害虫
The only problems are the pests.
许多地方有老鼠或蚊子
You see, most places have mice or mosquitoes.
而我们有...
We have...
龙
... dragons.
换做其他人就逃了  可我们不走
Most people would leave, but not us.
我们是维京海盗
We're Vikings.
我们以顽固著称
We have stubbornness issues.
我名叫卡嗝
My name is Hiccup.
不是个好名字  但好歹不算最差
Great name, I know. But it's not the worst.
父母相信骇人听闻的名字
Parents believe a hideous name will
能吓走山怪山精
frighten off Gnomes and Trolls.
好像我们"迷人"的维京风度还不够吓人
Like our charming Viking demeanor wouldn't do that.
早上好
Morning.
-你在这干嘛  -回去
- What are you doing here? - Get inside!
回屋里去
Get back inside!
卡嗝  他怎么又出来了
Hiccup! What is he doing out again...
你出来干什么  回去
What are you doing out? Get inside!
他是伟岸的史推克  部落首领
That's Stoick the Vast, Chief of the tribe.
听说他在婴儿时期
They say that when he was a baby he popped
曾把一条龙的脑袋齐肩削去
a dragon's head clean off its shoulders.
我相信吗  能不信吗
Do I believe it? Yes, I do.
都有些什么龙
What have we got?
巨齿龙  奈德龙  双头龙
Gronckles, Nadders, Zipplebacks... Oh,
还有一群凶煞梦魇
and hordes of Monstruous Nightmares.
有夜煞吗
Any Night Furys?
-目前没有  -很好
- None so far. - Good.
点燃火柱
Light the torches!
欢迎加入猎龙盛会
Oh, nice of you to join the party.
我还以为你已经被吃掉了
I thought you'd been carried off.
谁  我吗  算了吧
Who? Me? Nah, come on...
我太强壮了  不合它们胃口
I'm way too muscular for their taste.
他们不知道拿我怎么办
They wouldn't know what to do with all... this.
它们需要牙签吧  不是吗
Well, they need toothpicks, don't they?
这个语气不善
The meathead with the attitude and
装着假肢的蠢蛋名叫嘉伯
interchangeable hands, is Gobber.
我从小就在他手下当学徒
I have been his apprentice ever since I was little.
好吧  我现在也不大
Well, littler
我们转移到沼泽防御区
We move to the moor defenses.
在那用弹弩反击
We'll counterattack with the catapults.
看吧  这就是村庄老房子新的原因
See? Old village. Lots and lots of new houses.
射击
Fire!
那是小鱼脚
Oh, and that's Fishlegs
鼻涕唠
Snotlout
双胞胎悍夫奈和暴芙奈
The twins, Ruffnut and Tuffnut...
还有
And...
雅丝翠
Astrid.
他们的工作酷多了
Aww, their job is so much cooler.
让我出去  我要立功扬名
Oh, come on. Let me out, please. I need to make my mark!
你的名声已经够响亮了  简直臭名昭著
Oh, you have made plenty of marks. All in the wrong places.
求你  只要两分钟  我要杀条龙
Please, 2 minutes. I'll kill a dragon.
我的生活就会一片大好
My life will get infinitely better.
说不定还能找个女朋友
I might even get a date.
你举不起锤子  挥不动斧头
You can't lift a hammer. You can't swing an axe.
甚至扔不了这个
You can't even throw one of these.
我承认  但我可以用这个
Okay, fine, but this will throw it for me.
看  我就说吧
See, now this right here is what I'm talking about.
这只是小小的校准问题
But it... it's a mild calibration issue.
卡嗝  如果你想出去和龙战斗
Hiccup, if you ever want to get out there to fight dragons,
你就必须改变...
you need to stop all....
这个
... this.
可你指着我全身上下
But you just pointed to all of me.
正是如此
Yes, that's it.
你从头到尾都要改
Stop being all of you.
明白了吧
Oh, yes.
先生  你在玩火
You sir, are playing a dangerous game...
让我这块维京璞玉蒙尘
... keeping this much raw Vikingness contained.
-后果很严重  -我等着瞧
- There will be consequences! - I take my chances.
去磨剑  马上
Sword, sharpened, now!
总有一天我要出去
One day I'll get out there.
因为在这里杀死一条龙意味着全部
Because killing a dragon is everything around here.
一条奈德龙能让我小有名气
A Nadderhead is sure to get me at least noticed.
巨齿龙比较难对付
Gronckles are tough.
除掉其中一只肯定能让我交到女朋友
Taking down one of those would definitely get me a girlfriend.
至于双头龙
A Zippleback...
它属珍稀物种  双头意味着双倍地位
Exotic, two heads, twice the status.
他们发现我们的船了
They found the ship!
集中火力攻打低岸
Concentrate fire over the lower bank!
快点
Hurry up!
射击
Fire!
还有凶煞梦魇
And then, there's the Monstruous Nightmare.
只有维京精英才敢捕杀它们
Only the best Vikings go after those.
它们喜欢让自己着火
They have this nasty habit of setting themselves on fire.
装弹
Reload!
我来对付它
I'll take care of this.
但终极战利品是谁都没见过的龙
But the ultimate prize is the dragon no one's ever seen.
我们称之为...
We call it the...
-夜煞  -趴下
- Night Fury! - Get down!
跳
Jump!
这种龙不偷粮食  从不露面
This thing never steals food, never shows itself, and...
从不失手
... never misses.
没人杀过夜煞
No one has ever killed a Night Fury.
所以我才要成为第一个
That's why I'm going to be the first.
注意堡垒  卡嗝  我要出去
Mind the fort, Hiccup. They need me out there.
待在这  别乱动
Stay!... Put!
就待那儿
There.
你明白我的意思
You know what I mean.
-卡嗝  你在做什么  -回来
- Hiccup, what are you doing? - Come back here!
我知道  马上回来
Yeah, I know, be right back!
小心点
Mind yourself!
这些怪物还有点力气
The devils still have some juice in them.
快点
Come on.
给我一个射击的目标
Give me something to shoot at. Give me something to shoot at.
我打中了吗  我打中了
Oh! I hit it? Yes, I hit it!
有人看到了吗
Did anybody see that?
没说你
Except for you.
-别让它们跑了  -好
- Do not let them escape! - Right!
你喷不出火了
You're all out.
还有一件事没告诉你们
Oh, and there's one more thing you need to know...
对不起  爸爸
Sorry, Dad.
可我打中了一条夜煞
Okay, but I hit a Night Fury.
这次和以前不同  爸爸
It's not like the last few times, Dad!
我真的打中了...
I mean, I really actually hit...
当时你们在忙  我一击即中
You guys were busy and I had a very clear shot.
它掉到黑暗角去了
It went down just off Raven Point.
我们要派搜寻队去...
Let's get a search party out there before...
闭嘴
Stop!
别说了
Just, stop!
每次你一出来就会引起灾难
Every time you step outside disaster falls.
你还嫌我的麻烦不够多吗
Can you not see that I have bigger problems?
冬天就要来了  我得养活一村子人
Winter is almost here and I have an entire village to feed!
说句知心话  村里的人少吃点也没事
Between you and me, the village could do
难道你不这么觉得吗
with a little less feeding, don't you think?
这不是开玩笑  卡嗝
This isn't a joke, Hiccup!
这么简单的命令  你怎么就不听呢
Why can't you follow the simplest orders?
我控制不了  我一看到龙就想杀了它
I, I can't stop myself. I see a dragon and I have to just...
我本性如此  爸爸
... kill it. You know, it's who I am, Dad.
你能做很多事  卡嗝
Oh, you are many things, Hiccup,
但绝对杀不了龙
but a dragon killer is not one of them.
回屋里去  带他回去
Get back to the house. Make sure he gets there.
我来处理他惹的麻烦
I have his mess to clean up.
干得好
Quite the performance.
我没见过比这更糟的了  真了不起
I've never seen any one mess up that badly. That helped!
承蒙夸奖  我继续努力
Thank you. Thank you. I was trying.
-我真的打中了  -当然  卡嗝
- I really did hit one. - Sure, Hiccup.
-他从不听我说  -那是家族遗传
- He never listens. - Well, it runs in the family.
要不就满脸失望和愤怒
And when he does, it's always with this disappointed scowl
好像有人克扣了他三文治上的肉
like someone skimped on the meat in his sandwich.
打扰一下  女侍  恐怕你
Excuse me, barmaid. I'm afraid you
弄错我想要的儿子了
brought me the wrong offspring.
我点的是肌肉发达的大个子男孩
I ordered an extra large boy with beefy arms.
还要有勇气和荣誉
Extra guts and glory on the side.
这个却是会说话的鱼骨头
This here. This is a talking fish bone!
你完全想错了
Now, you're thinking about this all wrong.
这和你的外表无关
It's not so much what you look like.
他不能忍受的是你的内在
It's what's inside that he can't stand.
谢谢你的总结
Thank you for summing that up.
重点是这不适合你
Look, the point is, stop trying so
不要再勉为其难了
hard to be something you're not.
我只想成为你们当中的一员
I just want to be one of you guys.
我们不消灭它们  就会被它们消灭
Either we finish them or they'll finish us.
这是除掉它们的唯一办法
It's the only way we'll be rid of them.
找到并毁掉龙的巢穴  它们就会离开
If we find the nest and destroy it, the dragons will leave.
它们会去寻找另一个家园
They'll find another home.
趁海水结冰前我们再搜寻一次
One more search, before the ice sets in.
那些船只会有去无回
Those ships never come back.
我们是维京海盗  这是职业病
We're Vikings. It's an occupational hazard.
谁愿意和我去
Now who's with me?
好吧  留下来的人负责照顾卡嗝
Alright,... those who stay will look after Hiccup.
这才像样
That's more like it.
我去收拾我的底衣
I'll pack my undies.
不  你留下训练新兵
No, I need you to stay, and train some new recruits.
好极了  我在忙时卡嗝可以看店
Oh, perfect, yeah. And while I'm busy Hiccup can cover the store.
溶铁  磨刀片  还有很多时间独处
Molten steel, razor sharp blades, lots of time to himself...
绝对不会出事
What could possibly go wrong?
我要拿他怎么办  嘉伯
Oh, what am I going to do with him, Gobber?
让他和其他人一起训练
Put him in training with the others.
-我是认真的  -我也是
- No, I'm serious. - So am I.
你还没放龙出来  他就死了
He'd be killed before you let the first dragon out of its cage.
-这可不一定  -我很肯定
- Oh, you don't know that. - I do know that.
-不  你弄错了  -我不会错
- No, you don't - No, actually, I do.
-不  你错了  -你知道他的德性
- No, you don't. - Listen, you know what he's like.
从他会爬起他就与众不同
From the time he could crawl he's been... different.
他从不听我说
He doesn't listen.
注意力持续时间比麻雀还短
He has the attention span of a sparrow.
我带他去打渔  他却跑去猎山精
I take him fishing and he goes hunting for.. for Trolls!
山精的确存在  它们会偷袜子
Trolls exist! They steal your socks.
可只偷左脚的  为什么呢
But only the left ones. What's with that?
-我小时候...  -又来了
- When I was a boy... - Oh, here we go.
我父亲让我拿头撞石头
My father told me to bang my head
我照做了
against a rock,... and I did it.
我觉得这不合理  但我没质疑他
I thought it was crazy, but I didn't question him.
你知道后来怎么样了吗
And you know what happened?
-你患上头痛  -石头裂成两半
- You got a headache. - That rock split in two.
我从此知道了维京海盗的能力  嘉伯
It taught me what a Viking could do, Gobber.
他能摧毁大山  移平森林
He could crush mountains, level forests,...
驾驭海洋
... tame seas!
我从小就知道自己的能力和责任
Even as a boy I knew what I was, what I had to become...
卡嗝却不是这样
Hiccup is not that boy.
你阻止不了他  史推克
You can't stop him, Stoick.
你只能帮他作好准备
You can only prepare him.
我知道这不中听  但事实是
I know it seems hopeless, but the truth is
你不可能永远保护他
you won't always be around to protect him.
他还会出去  可能现在已经出去了
He's going to get out there again. He's probably out there now.
神明都不眷顾我
Oh, the Gods hate me.
有人丢了刀  有人丢杯子
Some people lose their knife or their mug.
我却丢了一条龙
No, not me! I managed to lose an entire dragon.
我成功了吗  我真的成功了
Oh, wow? I.. I did it? Oh, I did it!
这下一切问题都解决了
This fixes everything. Yes!
我打败了这只凶兽
I have brought down this mighty beast!
我要杀了你  龙先生
I'm gonna kill you, dragon.
我要挖出你的心脏
I'm gonna... I'm gonna cut out your
把它拿去给我的父亲
heart and take it to my father.
我是一名维京海盗
I'm a Viking.
我是维京海盗
I'm a Viking!
这是我做的
I did this.
卡嗝
Hiccup.
爸爸
Dad? Uh...
我有话和你说
I have to talk to you, Dad.
我也要和你谈谈  儿子
I need to speak with you too, son.
是时候让你学习和龙战斗了
I think it's time you to learned to fight dragons.
我不想和龙战斗
I don't want to fight dragons.
-什么  -什么
- What? - What?
-你先说  -不  你先说
- Uh, you go first. - No, no, you go first.
好吧  如你所愿
All right. You got your wish.
降龙训练  明天早上开始
Dragon training. You start in the morning.
天啊  我应该先说的
Oh man, I should have gone first.
我在想  你知道的
Uh, cause I was thinking. You know, we have a
我们有很多降龙维京人  但是
surplus of dragon fighting Vikings but,...
我们没有足够的维京面包师
Do we have enough bread-making Vikings,
或是维京修屋工
or small home repair Vikings...
-你会需要这个的  -我不想和龙战斗
- You'll need this. - I don't want to fight dragons.
别胡扯了  你很想的
Oh come on, yes you do.
这么说吧  爸爸  我不能杀龙
Rephrase. Dad, I can't kill dragons.
但你一定得杀
But you will kill dragons.
不  我确定肯定以及一定我不会
No, I'm really very extra sure that I won't.
-是时候了  卡嗝  -你听不到我说的吗
- It's time, Hiccup. - Can you not hear me?
这不是开玩笑  儿子
This is serious, son.
当你拿起这把斧子  你就与我们同在
When you carry this axe, you carry all of us with you.
像我们一样行走  像我们一样交流
You walk like us. You talk like us.
像我们一样思考
You think like us.
不仅仅是斧子
No more of... this.
你替我决定了我的人生
You just gestured to all of me.
-说定了吗  -都是你的一面之词
- Deal? - This conversation is feeling very one-sided.
说定了吗
Deal?
说定了
Deal.
很好
Good.
努力训练
Train hard.
我会回来的  也许吧
I'll be back. Probably.
我会在这的  可能吧
And I'll be here, maybe.
欢迎来到驯龙场
Welcome to dragon training.
无路可退了
No turning back.
真希望狠狠烧它们
I hope I get some serious burns.
我希望我肩膀或者腰上有把大槌
I'm hoping for some mauling, like on my shoulder or lower back.
是啊  留下伤疤就有意思了
Yeah, it's only fun if you get a scar out of it.
可不是嘛  伤痛  我喜欢
Yeah, no kidding, right? Pain, love it.
这下好了  谁让他进来的?
Oh, great, who let him in?
开始吧  表现最佳的新兵
Lets get started. The recruit who does best,
将有幸在全村人面前
will win the honor of killing his first
亲手屠龙
dragon in front of the entire village.
卡嗝都已经杀了一条夜煞了
Hiccup already killed a night fury,
这么说他失去资格还是...?
so does that disqualify him or...?
我能不能转到与真正的维京人一个班?
Can I transfer to the class with the cool vikings?
别担心  你个子小又单薄
Don't worry. You're small and you're weak,
最不容易被攻击
that will make you a less of a target.
它们会以为你是病患或者疯子
They'll see you as sick or insane and go
转而进攻那些维京少年
after the more viking-like teens instead.
这扇门后面藏着不同种的龙
Behind these doors are just a few of the
你们要学会如何击败它们
many species you will learn to fight.
-致命奈德龙  -速度  8  护甲  16
- The Deadly Nadder.  - Speed: 8, Armor: 16.
-凶恶双头龙  -隐身11秒  可隐身两次
- the Hideous Zippleback. - 11 stealth, times two.
-凶煞梦魇  -喷火攻击  15
- The Monstrous Nightmare.  - Fire Power: 15.
-极度恐怖  -攻击力  8  毒液附加  12
- The Terrible Terror. - Attack: 8, Venom: 12.
能不能闭嘴
Can you stop that!
-还有巨齿龙  -下颚攻击力  8
- And the Gronckle. - Jaw Strength: 8.
等等  你不先教教我们吗
Woah, woah, wait, aren't you going to teach us first?
我认为  实战出真理
I believe in learning on the job.
今天是生存训练
Today is about survival.
被撞倒就死定了
If you get blasted, you're dead.
动作快  你首先最需要什么
Quick! What's the first thing you're going to need?
-医生?  -速度值加5?
- A doctor? - 5 speed?
-盾?  -盾  去拿
- A shield? - shield. Go.
如果在盾与剑之间选择
Your most important piece of equipment is your shield.
还是要优先选择盾
If you must make a choice between a sword or a shield.
举起盾牌
Take the shield.
-这是我的盾  -那里还有好多盾
- Get your hands off my shield. - There's like a million shields.
拿那个  上面有花  女孩子都喜欢花
Take that one. It has a flower on it. Girls like flowers.
现在这上面有血花了
Oops, now this one has blood on it.
悍夫奈和暴芙奈  你俩出局了
Tuffnut, Ruffnut, your out.
-什么  -什么
- What? - What?
这些盾还有一个用途  干扰
Those shields are good for another thing. Noise.
虚虚实实  躲开龙的攻击
Make lots of it and throw off a dragon's aim.
每条龙都有攻击次数限制
All dragons have a limited number of shots.
巨齿龙能攻击几次?
How many does a gronckle have?
-五次?  -不  六次
- Five? - No, six.
对  六次  正好你们六个
Right, six. That's one for each of you.
小鱼脚  出局
Fishlegs, out.
卡嗝  躲进去
Hiccup, get in there!
我说  我搬到地窖里了
So anyway, I moved into my parent's basement?
有空你该过来练习一下
You should come by sometimes to work out,
你需要练习
you look like you work out.
鼻涕唠  你出局了
Snotlout, your done.
-好像就剩我俩了  -不  只有你
- So I guess its just you and me. - Nope, just you.
最后一击
One shot left.
卡嗝
Hiccup!
六击结束  回去睡觉吧  你这头肥猪
And that's 6. Go back to bed you overgrown sausage.
还有机会  别担心
You'll get another chance. Don't you worry.
记住  龙  总是...
Remember, a dragon will always...
无时无刻地寻求杀戮
... always go for the kill.
你为什么不杀我
So why didn't you?
这太愚蠢了
Well this was stupid.
你怎么不飞走
Why don't you just fly away?
雅丝翠  你今天的问题出在哪儿
Alright, where did Astrid go wrong in the ring today?
俯身时机不对  太草率
I mistimed my sommersault dive. It was sloppy.
它看穿了我的翻身
It threw off my reverse tumble.
-我们注意到了  -不  做得好  这就是你的风格
- Yeah, we noticed. - No, no you were great. That was so Astrid.
他说得对  你得坚持
She's right. You have to be tough on yourselves.
卡嗝的问题出在哪儿
Where did Hiccup go wrong?
-他就不该来吗  -他居然没被吃了
- Uh, he showed up? - He didn't get eaten.
他从来都找不准位置
He's never where he should be.
谢了  雅丝翠  你们得慢慢消化
Thank you, Astrid. You need to live and breathe this stuff.
驯龙图鉴...  这里面包含
The dragon manual... everything we
所有我们所知的龙的种类
know about every dragon we know of.
今夜龙不会进攻  赶紧看
No attacks tonight. Hurry up.
-等等  你是说看书?  -在有生之年?
- Wait? You mean read? - While we're still alive?
既然能屠龙
Why read words when you can just kill the
读书有何用?
stuff the words tell you stuff about?
我读了有七遍了
Oh, I've read it like 7 times.
上面说水龙会把沸水喷射到你脸上
There's this water dragon that sprays boiling water at your face
还说有一种龙能把自己埋上一周
And there's this other one that buries itself for like a week...
听起来不错  有机会我会拜读
Yeah, sounds great. There was a chance I was going to read that.
但现在...
But now...
你们看吧  我找些东西试手
You guys read, I'll go kill something.
-我们一起看吗  -你看吧
- So I guess we'll share? - Read it.
就剩我了?  好  我们...明天见
All mine then? Wow. So, okay. I'll see you uh,... tomorrow.
龙族分类
Dragon classifications
攻击型  恐惧型  魔法型
Strike class, fear class, mystery class.
雷鼓龙  隐匿型龙种
Thunder Drum. This reclusive dragon
栖息于海蚀洞与黑色潮汐塘中
inhabits sea caves and dark tide pools.
受惊吓时会发出震荡波
When startled, the Thunder Drum produces a
近距离接触会导致死亡
concussive sound that can kill a man at close range.
极度危险  格杀勿论
Extremely dangerous. Kill on sight.
伐木龙  此种巨龙拥有剃刀型龙翼
Timberjack: This gigantic creature has razor-sharp wings
能将苍天大树一劈为二
that can slice through full-grown trees.
极度危险  格杀勿论
Extremely dangerous. Kill on sight.
颅骨龙  喷出沸水伤害猎物  极度危险...
Skulldren: Sprays scalding water on its victim. Extremely dangerous...
小丑龙  即使幼龙也能喷射酸液  格杀勿论
Changeling: Even newly hatch dragons can spray acid. Kill on sight.
巨齿龙  双头龙  刺龙
Gronckle, Zippleback, the Skrill,
碎骨龙  致命耳语龙
Bonesnapper, Whispering Death.
烧死猎物  活埋猎物  掐死猎物
Burns its victims. Buries its victims. Chokes its victims.
将猎物内脏取出
Turns victims inside out.
极度危险  极度危险
Extremely dangerous.... Extremely dangerous....
格杀勿论  格杀勿论  格杀勿论
Kill on sight.... Kill on sight.... Kill on sight....
夜煞  速度未知  体长未知
Night Fury.Speed unknown. Size unknown.
雷神与死神的邪恶后裔
The unholy offspring of lightning and death itself.
尚无此龙数据
Never engage this dragon.
倘若遭遇  伺机隐藏  祈福保命
Your only chance:  Hide and pray it does not find you.
它们接近了  我可以感觉得到
I can almost smell them. They're close.
把定
Steady.
-开进去  -左满舵
- Take us in. - Hard to port.
地狱犬之门
The hell hounds gate.
左满舵
Hard to port.
那个  我刚好发现
Hey, you know, I just happened to notice,
书上没有关于夜煞的记载
the book had nothing on night furys.
有没有其它图鉴  或者续篇
Is there like another book? Or a sequel?
或者关于夜煞的小册子
Maybe a little night fury pamphlet?
小心  卡嗝  你怎么心不在焉
Focus Hiccup! You're not even trying.
今天训练如何攻击
Today is all about attack!
奈德龙步行时快而轻盈
Nadder's are quick and light on their feet.
你们必须更胜一筹才行
You be quicker and lighter.
别逼我质疑你的教学水平
I'm really beginning to question your teaching methods.
寻找它的盲点  每条龙都有盲点
Look for its blind spot. Every dragon has one.
找到盲点  以此躲避  再伺机攻击
Find it. Hide in it, and strike.
-你不洗澡的吗  -要是不喜欢
- Do you ever bathe? - You don't like it,
你自己来啊
then just get your own blind spot.
我给你来一下如何
How about I give you one?
盲点  有  死穴  不多
Blind spot, yes. Death spot, not-so-much.
该怎么偷偷接近夜煞?
Hey, hey, so how would one sneak up on a night fury?
没人见过  就算见到了也活不下来
No one's ever met one, and lived to tell the tale.
现在  给我进去
Now, get in there!
我知道  只是假设而已...
I know, I know but hypothetically...
小心  宝贝儿  我来对付
Watch out, babe, I'll take care of this.
阳光太刺眼了  雅丝翠
The sun was in my eyes, Astrid.
我能怎样  遮住太阳吗
What do you want me to do? Block out the sun?
我能做到  但现在没时间
I can do that. I don't have time right now.
-有人见过龙打盹吗  -卡嗝
- Has anyone ever seen one napping? - Hiccup!
卡嗝
Hiccup!
-战场上爱的火花  -她能行的
- Love on the battlefield. - She could do better.
让我来...你为什么不...
L-let me... Why don't you..
漂亮  雅丝翠
Well done, Astrid.
你是在儿戏吗
Is this some kind of a joke to you?
我们迟早要接过父辈的旗帜
Our parent's war is about to become ours.
想清楚你站在哪边
Figure out which side your on.
你没牙齿吗
Huh? Toothless.
我明明记得你应该有...
I could of sworn you have...
牙齿
... teeth.
不  不  不
Uh, uh,... no, no,... no...
我...我没有鱼啦
I... I don't have anymore.
接着它一转身  一口咬下我的手
And with one twist, he took my hand and swallowed it whole.
从它的眼神我知道  我一定很美味
And I saw the look in his face. I was delicious.
它一定跟其它龙说过  因为一个月内
He must have passed the word, because it wasn't a month
另一条龙吃了我的腿
Before another one of them took my leg.
你的手在龙腹中感觉不奇怪吗
Isn't it weird to think that your hand was inside a dragon?
要是你的大脑依然可以控制它
Like, if your mind was still in control of it,
你大可从龙腹里把它宰了
you could have killed the dragon from the inside.
把龙心碾碎  或者怎么怎么的
By crushing his heart or something.
我发誓  我现在生气极了
I swear, I'm so angry right now.
我一定要为你的手脚报仇
I'll avenge your beautiful hand and your beautiful foot.
我会砍下所遇到每条龙的腿...认真的!
I'll chop of the legs of every dragon l fight... with my face!
你要砍的是龙翼和龙尾
No. It's the wings and the tails you really want.
如果它飞不了  就无路可逃
If it can't fly, it can't get away.
不能飞的龙  就是死龙一条
A downed dragon is a dead dragon.
好吧  我去睡觉了
Alright, I'm off to bed.
你们也早点睡  明天要对付大家伙
You should be too. Tomorrow we get to the big boys.
虽然进步缓慢  但我们还是到了凶煞梦魇
Slowly but surely, making our way up to monstrous nightmare.
谁能有幸宰了它呢
But who'll win the honor of killing it?
肯定是我  这是命  明白吗
It's gonna be me. It's my destiny. See?
你妈同意你纹身吗
Your mom let you get a tattoo?
不是纹身  是胎记
It's not a tattoo. It's a birth mark.
你出生时我就跟你在一起
Okay, I've been stuck with you since
怎么没看到
birth and that was never there before.
你没从左边看而已
Yes, it was. You've just never seen me to the left side until now.
无牙仔  我给你带了早餐
Hey, toothless. I brought breakfast.
那个...希望你有胃口
I hope... I hope you're hungry.
好吧  这挺恶心的
Okay, that's disgusting.
我带了些鲑鱼  一些美味的冰岛鳕鱼
I got some salmon, some nice lcelandic cod,
还有整条熏鳗鱼
and a whole smoked eel.
不要吗  好吧
No, no, no, no,... no.... okay.
好吧  我也不怎么喜欢鳗鱼
Yeah, I don't really like eel much either.
对了  这样很好  忽视我的存在
That's it. That's the good stuff. Aah, don't you mind me.
我还是来这关心我的事
I'll just be back here, minding my own business.
没事的...
Its okay...
没事  没事...
Okay, okay...
搞定  不差嘛  挺有用的
Okay, that's not too bad. It works.
不  不  不
No, no, no, no, no, no... !
天呐  成功了
Oh my... its working!
我做到了
Yes, yes, I did it.
今天练习团队配合
Today, is about teamwork.
龙头要是被淋湿  他就不能喷火了
Now, a wet dragon head can't light its fire.
凶恶双头龙极度狡猾
The hideous zippleback is extra tricky.
一个头喷气  一个头点火
One head breathes gas. The other head lights it.
你们要分出龙头的功能
Your job is to know which is which.
锋利的牙齿  喷射出毒液  来腐蚀食物
Razor-sharp serrated teeth, and injects venom for predigestion.
更喜欢伏击  踩碎食物
Prefers ambush attack, crushing its victims.
闭嘴好吗
Will you please stop that?!
不管哪个龙头出现  我都要...
If that dragon shows either of his faces, I'm gonna...
在那儿
There!
是我们  白痴
Hey, its us, idiots!
你屁股越来越挺了  我们看成龙了
Your butts are getting bigger we thought you were a dragon.
那曲线看起来就像是龙屁...
Not that theres anything wrong with a dragon-ass fig...
等等...
Wait...
我受伤了  我很受伤
Oh!... oh, I'm hurt! I am very much hurt!
生存几率微乎其微
Chances of survival are dwindling into single digits now.
不是这个头
Oh! Wrong head.
小鱼脚
Fishlegs!
就是现在  卡嗝
Now Hiccup!
拜托
Aww, come on...
卡嗝
Hiccup!
退后  退后
Back,... Back, back!
我话不说两遍
Now don't you make me tell you again!
对  没错  回到洞里去吧
Yes, thats right. Back into your cage!
好好反省一下
Now think about what you've done.
那么  训练结束了吗
Okay, sooo, were we done?
我还有事要去...
Cause I have some things I need to uh...
那明天见
Yep, I'll see you tomorrow.
嗨
Hey!
-什么情况  -你怎么做到的
- What was that? - How did you do that?
我把斧子留在竞技场了  你们先走
I left my axe back in the ring. You guys go on ahead.
我回头再找你们
I'll catch up with you.
来会会极度恐惧
Meet the Terrible Terror.
哈  这大小就好像我的...
Ha! It's like the size of my...
把它弄掉
Oooh!... Get it off!
好疼  疼死了
Oh, I'm hurt! I am very much hurt!
他可比你强多了
Wow! He's better than you ever were.
什么
What?
太棒了
Ooh, great.
卡嗝
Hiccup.
卡嗝  是你吗
Hiccup? Are you in there?
雅丝翠  嗨  雅丝翠  你好呀
Astrid, hey. Hi, Astrid. Hi astrid. Hi Astrid
我一般不多管别人闲事  但你的举止真是很诡异
I normally don't care what people do, but you're acting weird.
好吧  更诡异了
Well, weirder.
你好歹找到了巢穴吧
Well, I trust you found the nest at least?
连影子都没有
Not even close.
棒极了
Excellent.
希望你这里有点好消息
I hope you had a little more success than me.
如果你的好消息是指
Well, if by success, you mean that your
身为家长不用再头痛了
parenting troubles are over with,...
那就算是吧
.. then, yes.
恭喜你  史推克  大家都松了口气
Congratulations Stoick! Everyone is so relieved.
从头到尾  焕然一新哈
Out with the old, and in with the new, right?
没人会想念以前那个旧麻烦
No one will miss that old nuisance.
村子要举办一场晚会来庆祝
The village is throwing a party to celebrate.
他不在吗
He's gone?
下午一般都不在  但这又不能怪他
Um, yeah, most afternoons, but who can blame him?
我是说  做一个名人可不容易啊
I mean, the life of a celebrity is very rough.
他现在每次经过村子
He can barely walk through the village
都被一群新粉丝围堵
without being swarmed by his new fans.
-卡嗝?  -谁会想到呢
- Hiccup? - Who would have thought it, eh?
他对付那群野兽自有一套
He has this way with the beasts.
好吧  伙计  我们要飞得更慢更稳些
Okay there, bud, were gonna take this nice and slow.
走吧  三号  不  四号位置
Here we go. Here we go. Position three, no, four.
好  是时候出发了
Alright, it's go time. It's go time.
加油啊  伙计  加油
Come on, buddy. Come on, buddy.
成功了
Yes, it works!
对不起
Sorry!
是我不好
That's my fault.
我知道了啦  四号  呃  三号位置
Yeah, yeah, I'm on it. Position four, uh, three.
冲啊  宝贝
Yeah! Go baby!
太帅了  风就在我...
Oh, this is amazing! The wind in my...
我的小抄
... cheat sheet!
停下
Stop!
不
No!
我的天啊
Oh, gosh! Oh, God!
不
Oh no!
好吧  你要自己调整角度
Alright. Okay. You gotta kinda angle yourself!
不不不  回到下面来接我
Okay. No, no, no... come back down towards me.
下来...
Come back down... oww!
不是吧
Come on...
不  谢谢  我不饿
Uh, no thanks. I'm good.
里面也不怎么防火吧
Not so fire-proof on the inside, are you?
给你
Here you go.
我们根本就不了解你们
Everything we know about you guys is wrong.
爸爸  你回来了
Dad, you're back!
嘉伯不在  那个...
Gobber's not here, so...
我知道
I know.
我是来找你的
I came looking for you.
-是吗  -你瞒着我什么秘密
- You did? - You've been keeping secrets.
是吗
I have?
你觉得你能瞒我多久呢
Just how long did you think you could hide it from me?
我  我不知道你
I... I don't know what you...
无论岛上发生什么  都逃不过我的眼睛
Nothing happens on this island, without me hearing about it.
那么  我们谈谈龙吧
So, lets talk... about that dragon
爸爸  对不起
Dad, I'm so sorry.
我是准备告诉你  只是不知道该怎么...
I was going to tell you, I just didn't know how to uh...
-你没生气吗  -什么  这正是我的期望
- You're not upset? - What? I was hoping for this!
-是吗  -相信我
- Ah, you were? - And believe me...
一切只会更好  等到你
It only gets better. Just wait till you
第一次掏出奈德龙的内脏
spill a Nadder's guts for the first time...
第一次把巨齿龙的头挂在长矛上
... and mount your first Gronckle head on a spear.
太赞了  你真让我欣慰  儿子
What feeling! You really had me going there, son.
多年来我见过的最糟糕的维京海盗
All those years of the worst Viking Berk has ever seen.
欧丁神  真不容易  我差点就放弃你了
Odin, it was rough. I almost gave up on you.
原来你一直瞒着我
And all the while you were holding out on me.
伟大的托尔雷神
Oh, Thor almighty!
既然你在竞技场上表现出色
With you doing so well in the ring...
我们终于有话题可谈了
... we finally have something to talk about.
我带了样东西给你
I uh, I brought you something...
能在竞技场上保护你的安全
... to keep you safe in the ring.
谢谢
Wow, thanks.
你妈妈也希望让你戴上它
Your mother would wanted you to have it.
这是她铠甲的一半
It's half of her breast plate.
匹配的设计  好让她更近些  知道吗
Matching set. Keeps her... keeps her close, you know?
自豪地戴上吧  你值得拥有它
Wear it proudly. You deserve it.
你信守了承诺
You've held your end of the deal.
我真得去睡觉了
I should really get to bed.
-好  不错的谈话  -是啊
- Yes, good, okay, good talk. - Yeah...
那么明天家里见  好的
I'll see you back at the house. Great.
谢谢你过来
Thanks for stopping by and...
-还有这个  帽子  -我希望
- ... The uh... breast hat. - I hope
你喜欢  这个帽子
you like the, umm,... the hat.
晚安
Well, good night.
靠边站  我这次一定要赢
Stay out of my way. I'm winning this thing!
好吧  请随意
Good. Please. By all means.
这次我一定可以
This time! This time for sure!
不  你个半人半妖  吃耗子的呆子
No! No, son-of-a half troll, rat-eating munch bucket...!
等等  等等
Wait! Wait.
那回头见啦
So... later.
-别这么着急  -我快迟到了...
- Oh, oh! Not so fast! - I'm kinda late for...
什么  迟到个什么鬼
What! Late for what, exactly?
好了  安静  长老已做出了决定
Okay, quiet down. The elder has decided.
孩子  你成功了  卡嗝
Boy, you've done it! You've done it, Hiccup!
你可以亲手杀死一条龙了
You get to kill the dragon!
这才是我儿子
That's my boy!
耶  是啊  我都等不及了  我真是...
Yeah! Yes, I can't wait. I am so...
走吧  我们得走了
... leaving. We're leaving.
我们收拾行李吧
Let's pack up.
看来咱们要去旅行了
Looks like you and me are taking a little vacation.
永远的旅行
Forever.
搞什么?!  你在这干什么
What the... ? Uh, w.. what are you doing here?
我想知道是怎么回事
I want to know what's going on.
没有人会一下子这么出色
No one just get as good as you do.
尤其是你
Especially... you.
-快说  -我...
- Start talking. - I... I...
你是在和谁特训吗
Are you training with someone?
特训  我没有
Training? I didn't...
最好没有
It better not involve this.
我知道  这看起来是很糟  但是...
I know, this looks really bad but you see, this is...
好吧  你是对的
You're right. You're right. You're right.
我一直在撒谎
I... I'm through with the lies.
我一直在做额外装备
I've been making... outfits!
好吧  被你发现了  那就告诉大家好了
So, you got me. It's time everyone knew.
拖我回去  走吧  我们走吧
Drag me back. Go ahead. Here we go.
你为什么要这样
Oww. Why would you do that?
这下是为那些谎话
That's for the lies!
而这下  是为所有其它事
And that's... for everything else!
惨了
Oh man.
趴下
Get down!
快跑  快跑
Run! Run!
不  没事的  没事  她是朋友
No! No! it's okay. It's okay. She's a friend.
你吓到他了
You just scared him.
反而是我吓到他了?!
I scared him?
他是谁
Who is him?
雅丝翠  这是无牙仔  无牙仔  这是雅丝翠
Astrid, Toothless. Toothless, Astrid.
我们死定了
Dut, da da... we're dead.
你这是想去哪儿
Woah, woah woah. Where do you think your going?
伟大的欧丁神  不要  这...
Oh, great Odin! Don't. Oh, this is...
卡嗝  把我放下来
Hiccup, get me down from here!
那你先听我解释
You have to give me a chance to explain.
我才不要听你解释
I am not listening to anything you have to say!
那我不用说的  你只要看着就好
Then I won't speak. Just let me show you.
求你了  雅丝翠
Please, Astrid.
快带我下去
Now get me down!
无牙仔  下去吧  温柔点
Toothless, down. Gently.
我说吧  没什么好怕的
See, nothing to be afraid of.
无牙仔
Toothless?
你抽什么疯  你真不乖
What is wrong with you? Bad dragon!
他平时不会这样
He's uh, he's not usually like this.
哦  不
Oh, no!
无牙仔  你在搞什么  我们得给她留下好印象
Toothless, what are you doing? We need her to like us!
好吧  他在旋转了
And now he's spinning!
你根本毫无帮助  你个没用的爬虫
Thank you for nothing you useless reptile!
好吧  我错了  拜托快让我下来
Okay, I am sorry, I'm sorry. Just get me off of this thing.
好吧  我承认  这真是酷
Alright, I admit it. This is pretty cool.
真是不可思议  他也是
It's amazing. He's amazing.
现在怎么办
So what now?
卡嗝  明天就是你最后的考试
Hiccup, your final exam is tomorrow!
你心里也清楚吧
You know your gonna have to kill a...
你要杀死一条龙
Kill a dragon...
不用提醒我
Don't remind me.
无牙仔  怎么了
Toothless, what happening?
怎么回事
Whoa, what is it?
低下身子
Get down!
-怎么回事  -我不知道
- What's going on? - I don't know.
无牙仔  你得带我们出去  伙计
Toothless, you gotta get us out of here, bud.
他们好像在搬运猎物
It looks like they're hauling in their kill.
这跟我们有关系吗
What does that make us?
我爸爸绝不会想到是这种地方
What my dad wouldn't give to find this.
我们的食物就这么被扔进洞里
Oh, it's satisfying to know that all of
看到还真是让人感到欣慰
our food has been dumped down a hole.
他们一点都没吃
They're not eating any of it.
那是什么东西
What... was that?
好吧  伙计  我们得从这出去  马上
Alright, bud, we gotta get out of here. Now!
不  这就说得通了  这就好像一个大蜂巢
No, no, it totally makes sense. It's like a giant beehive.
他们是工蜂  而那就是他们的蜂后
They're the workers, and that's their queen.
正是它统治着他们  我们去找你爸爸
It controls them. Let's find your dad.
不  不
No, no.
不  还不行  他们会杀了无牙仔
No. Not yet. They'll kill Toothless.
雅丝翠  我们得好好想一想
Astrid, we have to think this through, carefully.
卡嗝  我们刚发现了龙的巢穴
Hiccup, we just discovered the dragon's nest.
自从最早的一批祖先定居此地  我们便一直在寻找
The thing we've been after since Vikings first sailed here.
现在你却要隐瞒不说
And you want to keep it secret?
就为了保护你的宠物  那条龙吗  你是认真的吗
To protect your pet, dragon? Are you serious?
是的
Yes.
好吧  那我们怎么办
Okay. Then what do we do?
给我点时间  明天我会想法子
Just give me until tomorrow. I'll figure something out.
好吧
Okay....
这下是因为你绑架我
That's for kidnapping me.
这下  是为了所有其它事
That's for... everything else.
你看什么看
What are you looking at?
好吧  我又可以在公共场合露面了
Well, I can show my face in public again.
要是以前有人告诉我
If someone had told me that in a few short weeks
卡嗝会在短短数周内  摇身一变
Hiccup will go from, well being... uh... Hiccup,
成为降龙训练中的佼佼者
to placing first in dragon training.
我会把他绑在桅杆上
Well, I would have tied him to a mast and
再开船把他送走  因为他肯定疯得不轻
shipped him off. For fear he'd gone mad.
你们也知道
And you know it.
而此时此刻
But, here we are.
没有人比我更加倍感自豪与惊叹
And no ones more surprised or more proud than I am.
今天  我的儿子成长为一名真正的维京海盗
Today my boy becomes a Viking!
今天  他已成为我们其中一员
Today he becomes one of us!
小心那条龙
Be careful with that dragon.
我担心的不是龙
It's not the dragon I'm worried about.
你要怎么办
What are you going to do?
了结这一切
Put an end to this.
我必须试一下
I have to try.
雅丝翠  要是出了意外
Astrid, if something goes wrong,
确保他们不会找到无牙仔
just make sure they don't find Toothless.
我会的  但你要保证不出意外
I will, just promise me it won't go wrong.
是时候了  卡嗝
It's time, Hiccup.
将它们打个一败涂地
Knock 'em dead.
要我肯定选那把锤子
I'd have gone for the hammer.
准备好了
I'm ready.
上吧  卡嗝  给它点颜色看看
Go on Hiccup, give it to him!
他在做什么
What is he doing?
没事的
It's okay, it's okay.
我和他们不同
I'm not one of them.
停止这场打斗
Stop the fight!
不  我要你们亲眼见证
No! I need you all to see this.
他们不是我们想的那样
They're not what we think they are.
我们不用非得杀了他们
We don't have to kill them.
我说停止战斗
I said stop the fight!
让开
Out of my way!
卡嗝
Hiccup!
这边
This way!
夜煞
Night fury!
好了  无牙仔  离开这儿
Alright, Toothless. Go! get out of here.
快走
Go, go!
不  爸爸  他不会伤害你
No, dad! dad, he won't hurt you!
无牙仔  住手
Toothless, stop!
不  不
No. No!
抓住它
Get him!
不  请别伤害它
No, no, please. Just don't hurt him
请别伤害它
Please. Don't hurt him
把它和其它龙关在一起
Put it with the others.
我早该知道
I should have known.
我早该看出迹象
I should have seen the signs.
-爸爸  -我们有过约定
- Dad? - We had a deal!
我知道  但那时我...
I know! We did, but that was before I...
好吧  一切都糟透了
oh, it's all so messed up.
竞技场的那一切...都是诡异和谎言吗
So everything in that ring... A trick? A lie?
我搞砸了  我早该告诉你
I screwed up. I should have told you before now.
是我的错  冲我发火吧  但是求你
Take this out on me, be mad at me, but please,
别伤害无牙仔
just don't hurt Toothless.
那条龙吗  你担心的就是这个吗
The dragon? That's what you're worried about?
那些差点被你害死的人呢
Not the people you almost killed?
他只是在保护我  他并不危险
He was just protecting me! he's not dangerous.
它们杀害了无数我们的族人
They've killed hundreds of us!
但我们杀了更多他的同伴
And we've killed thousands of them.
他们只是为了自卫  仅此而已
They defend themselves, that's all.
他们袭击我们是迫不得已
They raid us because they have to.
如果他们不带食物回去
If they don't bring enough food back,
就会被吃掉
they'll be eaten themselves.
他们的岛上有别的东西
There's something else on their island,
爸爸  有一条龙  他...
Dad. It's a dragon-like...
它们的岛屿?  你去过它们的巢穴吗
Their island? So, you've been to the nest?
-我有说到巢穴吗  -你怎么找到的?
- Did I say nest? - How did you find it?
不  我没有  是无牙仔带我去的
No, no, I didn't. Toothless did.
只有龙可以找到那个岛
Only a dragon can find the island.
不  爸爸  求你了  别这样
No, no, dad, no please. Its not what you think.
你不了解你面对的敌人
You don't know what your up against.
是你前所未见的那种
It's like nothing you've ever seen.
爸爸  我保证  你赢不了它
Dad, please, I promise you. You can't win this one!
爸爸  不要
Dad, no!
哪怕一次也好  你为什么就听不进去我的话呢
For once in your life, would you please just listen to me!
你和它们站在一起
You've thrown your lot in with them.
你不是维京人
You're not a viking.
你也不是我儿子
You're not my son!
备船
Ready the ships!
启航
Set sail!
向地狱犬之门进发
We head for Hell-hounds gate.
恶魔  带我们去你的老巢吧
Lead us home, devil.
糟透了  你一定难受极了
It's a mess. You must feel horrible.
你失去了所有  你父亲
You've lost everything. Your father,
你的部落  你最好的朋友
your tribe, your best friend.
谢谢你的总结
Thank you for summing that up.
我在树林里发现他时
Why couldn't I've killed that dragon,
为什么不干脆杀了他
when I found him the woods?
这样对大家都好
Would've been better for everyone.
对  换作是其他人肯定这么做
Yep, the rest of us would have done it.
为什么你偏偏下不了手
So, why didn't you?
为什么不杀了他
Why didn't you?
我不知道  我做不到
I don't know. I couldn't.
-这个不算答案  -为什么
- That's not an answer. - Why is this
这怎么突然变得对你如此重要
so important to you all of a sudden?
因为我想记住你现在所说的话
Because I want to remember what you say, right now.
老天爷  我是个软弱的胆小鬼
Ah, for the love of... I was coward, I was weak.
我连条龙都不想杀
I wouldn't kill a dragon!
你刚才说你不想杀?
You said wouldn't that time?
怎么都好  我就是不想
Whatever, I wouldn't!
三百年来  我是第一个
300 years and I'm the first viking
不想杀龙的维京人
who wouldn't kill a dragon.
但也是第一个龙骑士
First to ride one though.
所以呢
So?
我下不了手  因为他看起来和我一样害怕
I wouldn't kill him because he looked as frightened as I was.
我从他身上看到了自己
I looked at him and I saw myself.
我想他现在一定很害怕
I bet he's really frightened now.
你有何打算
What are you gonna do about it?
做一些蠢事吧
Probably something stupid.
好吧  蠢事你早就做了
Good, but you've already done that.
那就来一场疯狂的
Then something crazy!
这才像样
That's more like it.
守好位置  保持联系
Sound your positions! stay within earshot.
史推克  我刚才有所耳闻
Listen, Stoick, I was overhearing some of
一些船员...
the men just now and well, you know,...
对我们要去哪儿表示疑惑
some of them are wondering what it is we're up to here?
当然不包括我
Not me of course.
我知道你总会计划周详
I know you are always the man with the plan.
但是一些除我以外的人在疑惑
But some, not me, are wondering if
你是否有所计划
there is in fact a plan at all...
如果有  是什么计划呢
and what it might be?
找到龙巢  击溃它
Find the nest and take it.
当然  把它们放跑
Of course. Send them running.
老海盗的后备计划  简单而有效
The old viking fallback. Nice and simple.
靠边
Step aside.
驶向港口
Head to port.
你是想要被吃了吧
If you're planning on getting eaten,
我一定要和巨齿龙一起去
I'd definitely go with the Gronckle.
要是你脑袋灵光
You were wise to seek help
就得求助世界上最致命的武器
from the world's most deadly weapon.
那就是我
It's me.
-我喜欢这个计划  -我不...
- I love this plan! - I didn't...
你太疯狂了  我就喜欢这点
You're crazy. I like that.
那么  是什么计划
So, what is the plan?
这可不怎么有利于士气
That's not very encouraging.
难怪一直不见船回来
Oh, I was wondering where that went.
保持低姿  备好兵器
Stay low, and ready your weapons.
我们到了
We're here.
等等  你在干什么...
Wait, what are you...?!
没事的
It's okay... it's okay.
你要去哪儿
Where are you going?
得加一些东西帮你驾住龙
You're gonna need something to help you hold on.
我们敲破山门
When we crack this mountain open,
所有龙就会蜂拥而出
all hell is gonna break loose.
好吧  幸好我带了备用的底衣
... in my undies. Good thing I brought extras.
无论结果如何  今天要做个了断
No matter how this ends, it ends today.
结束了吗
Is that it?
我们胜利了
We've done it!
还没完
This isn't over!
列阵  拉石弹弓
Form your ranks. Pull together!
快撤
Get clear!
我滴雷神啊...那是什么东西
Beards of thor,... ! what is that?
欧丁神保佑
Odin, help us!
发射石弹
Catapults! Fire!
-回到船上去  -不
- Get to the ships! - No, nooo!
-好吧  那艘起火了  -我真蠢
- Not that one... - I was a fool.
带着大家逃到岛的远端
Lead the men to the far side of the island.
嘉伯  你也一起走
Gobber, go with the men.
我要留下看着你
I think I'll stay, just in case you're
免得你做出什么疯狂之举
thinking of doing something crazy.
只要我引开那个东西
I can buy them a few minutes if I give
就能拖延一点时间  让他们逃脱
that thing something to hunt for.
那加我一个岂不更好
Then I can double that time.
-来啊  -这边
- Here! - Oh, no. Here!
-跟我打  -不  跟我打
- Fight me! - No, me!
悍夫  暴芙  注意身后
Ruff, Tuff, watch your backs!
跟上  小鱼脚
Move, Fishlegs!
看啊  我们骑着龙  全都骑着龙
Look at us! we're on dragons! We're on dragons! All of us!
你那顽固的维京死脑筋能想得到吗
Every bit the bull-headed stubborn viking you ever were.
-小鱼脚  上去攻击  -好
- Fishlegs, break it down! - Okay.
头尾的重甲是为了
Heavily armored skull and tail made for
猛击和废碎敌人
bashing and crushing. Steer clear of both.
小眼大鼻孔  说明它主要依靠听力和嗅觉
Small eyes, large nostrils. Relies on hearing and smell.
好  阿唠和阿脚  留在它的盲点
Okay, Lout, Legs, hang in it's blind spot.
弄些噪音扰乱它
Make some noise. Keep it confused.
悍夫和暴芙  想法子找出它的死角
Ruff, Tuff, find out if it has a shot limit.
激怒它
Make it mad.
-那是我的专长  -扯吧你
- That's my specialty! - Since when?
地球人都知道我更会气人
Everyone knows I'm more irritating, see.
照我说的做  我尽快回来
Just do what I told you. I'll be back as soon as I can.
别担心  我们来掩护你
Don't worry! We got it covered!
-傻瓜  -呆子
- Fool! - Butto!
再见  你个螺栓
Bye, ya grendel!
这个东西没有死角
Um, this thing doesn't have a blind spot!
那儿
There!
去帮他们吧
Go help the others!
好  坚持住
Okay, hold on. Hold on.
-起作用了  -没错
- It's working! - Yeah, its working!
我控制不了巨齿龙了
I've lost power on the Gronckle!
鼻涕唠  别光傻看着
Snotlout, do something!
我很好
I'm okay!
好才怪
Less okay.
错不了  怎么了  伙计
I can't miss! Whats wrong, buddy?
眼睛里进东西了吗
You got something in your eye?
你真有海盗的范儿
Yeah, you're the viking!
爸爸
Dad?
好样的  伙计
You got it, bud!
卡嗝
Hiccup!
我很抱歉...
I'm sorry...
对我所做的一切
... for... for everything.
是...我也是
Yeah... me too.
你不必去那儿
You don't have to go up there.
我们是海盗  这是职业病
We're vikings. It's an occupational hazard
儿子  我为你骄傲
I'm proud to call you my son.
谢谢  老爸
Thanks, dad.
他来了
He's up!
去把鼻涕唠救出来
Get Snotlout outta there!
-这是我的活  -我先干的
- I'm on it! - I'm on it first!
喂  让我来骑
Hey, let me drive!
-别推我  -我要把你牙敲出来
- Don't push me! - I'll push your teeth out!
不敢相信居然有效
You know, I can't believe that worked.
-夜煞  -趴下
- Night fury! - Get down!
接到她了吗
Did you get her?
去吧
Go!
这家伙有翅膀  好吧  看看它能不能飞
This thing has wings. Okay, lets see if it can use them!
你觉得那招有效吗
You think that did it?
它会飞
Well, he can fly.
好了  无牙仔  该消失了  上吧  伙计
Okay, Toothless, time to disappear! Come on, bud!
来吧
Here it comes!
小心
Watch out!
好了  时间到  看看是否有效
Okay, times up. Let's see if this works.
来吧  你就这点能耐吗
Come on! Is that the best you can do?
振作一点  我们真棒  再坚持一会儿
Stay with me, buddy. We're good. Just a little bit longer.
准备  无牙仔  就是现在
Hold, Toothless. Now!
不...不
No... no!
卡嗝
Hiccup! Hiccup!
儿子
Son!
卡嗝
Hiccup!
儿子
Oh son!
这都是我的错
I did this.
我...我很抱歉
I'm s... I'm so sorry.
卡嗝
Hiccup!
他还活着  你把他活着带回来了
He's alive! you brought him back alive!
谢谢你...救了我儿子
Thank you... for saving my son.
算是救回来了吧
Well, you know, most of him.
你好  无牙仔
Hey, Toothless.
伙计  真高兴再见到你
Happy to see you too, buddy.
我...在我的房间里
Aawww, what... uh... I'm... in my house
你在我的房间里
You're in my house.
我爸爸知道你在这儿吗
Does my dad know your here?
好吧...好吧
Uh, what, oh, okay,... okay.
无牙仔  别这样  好吧
Toothless, no. Toothless! Aw, come on.
好吧  谢谢你  小家伙
Okay. Thanks, bud.
无牙仔  待着别动
Toothless, stay here.
来吧  伙计们  准备好  抓紧  我们走
C'mon guys. Get ready! hold on tight. Here we go!
什么
What?
我就知道  这不是真的吧
I knew it. I'm dead.
当然是  你干得很出色
No, but you give it your best shot.
你觉得如何
So, what do you think?
看  是卡嗝
Hey look, it's Hiccup!
卡嗝
Hiccup!
事实证明  我们只需做一下改变
It turns out, all we needed was a little more of... this.
你又擅自替我决定了吗
You just gestured to all of me?
不全都是  那腿是我的杰作
Well, most of you. That bit's my handiwork.
再加上一点卡嗝的光耀
With a little Hiccup flare thrown in.
你觉得好用吗
You think that'll do?
看来我还得做些调节
I might make a few tweaks.
这一下  是因为你害我担心
That's... for scaring me.
你以后不能总这样  因为...
What... what, is it always going to be this way? Because...
我想我能习惯
I could get used to it.
欢迎回家
Welcome home.
-夜煞  -趴下
- Night fury! - Get down!
准备好了吗
You ready?
这里是伯克村
This is Berk...
一年中九个月下雪  其它三个月下冰雹
It snows nine months of the year and hails the other three.
这儿生长的食物坚硬无味
Any food that grows here is tough and tasteless.
这儿的人更是有过之而无不及
The people that grow here are even more so.
唯一的好处就是宠物
The only upsides are the pets.
其它地方有小马或鹦鹉...
While other places have ponies or parrots...
而我们有...
We have...
龙
Dragons